Guide to the National Organization for Women, New York City Chapter (NOW-NYC) Records TAM.106
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
- Series IV: Committees, 1966-2006; 1970-2002; 19.58 Linear Feet in 41 manuscript boxes, a flat box, 3 oversized flat boxes, and 2 flat-file-folders
  Equal Rights Amendment (ERA) Task Force: This committee began as an ad-hoc committee in 1969 and soon thereafter became a subcommittee of the Legislative and Political Affairs Committee. In 1977, it became a standing committee. Files related to this committee contain materials on NOW-NYC's assistance to the Illinois chapter in its efforts towards ratification in the state legislature; copies of the 1980 publication "ERA Impact Clearinghouse," which lists state court cases relevant to the ratification struggle. Between 1981-1982, NOW-NYC conducted two large-scale assistance efforts: the Equality Riders Campaign that sent organizers to other states and the Message Brigade Campaign, which inundated legislators with pro-ERA letters. Other materials related to this committee include agendas, meeting minutes, cartoons, clippings, correspondence, press releases, event flyers, fact sheets, resources about the ERA, pamphlets, reports, schedules, Senate hearing transcripts, and voting records. (See also the NP Collection for business-size cards with the Equal Rights Amendment on them, and an "E.R.A. YES" bumper sticker.)
  Finance Committee: Materials related to this committee include annual reports, budgets, correspondence, agendas, minutes, fact sheets, policy statements, and financial resources.
  Friends of NOW-NYC: This committee included women in business, advertising, the nonprofit sector, education, and the arts who experienced successes measured by their earnings and level of responsibility. Members of this group were expected to contribute a minimum yearly contribution of $100 and were expected to participate in various NOW-NYC events as sources of professional advice. Materials related to this committee include mission statements, questionnaires, blank membership forms, press releases, memorandum, event flyers, and notes.
  Fundraising Committee: The flyers for many early NOW-NYC events appear in these folders including 1971's Women's Dance Project, the 5th Anniversary Christmas Party, and the NOW Boutique through which the committee sold clothing and cosmetics to raise money. Events from 1972 include the celebration of Susan B. Anthony's birthday and in 1973, NOW-NYC honored Sylvia Plath with a performance of her poetry entitled, "A Difficult Borning." Other materials related to this committee include commercial products, catalogues of cosmetics the committee used for the NOW-Boutique/Fashion Show, membership information, and promotional ideas.
  Image of Women Committee: In 1971, this committee was active in its campaign to reform advertising that was deemed offensive to women. The committee corresponded with numerous advertising agencies and corporations, namely National Airlines, whose campaign, "I'm Cheryl. Fly Me," incensed NOW committee members. In 1972, this committee produced reports recommending better reporting on women in the New York Times and the New York Daily New. On February 12, 1979, this committee renamed itself the Media Reform Committee. Materials related to these committees include print advertisements, brochures, clippings, correspondence, greeting cards, press releases, surveys, subject files, event flyers, fact sheets, reports, and speeches.
  Legislative Action Workers (L.A.W.) Committee: Materials related to this committee include agendas and committee goals.
  Legislative and Political Affairs Committee: This committee was formed in November 1968. Topics found within these folders include the annual State Lobby Day in Albany, New York in 1979 and 1982; the 1971 report, "Women and the City: How to Use the Machinery"; and information about NOW's legal action against the American Broadcasting Company (ABC), some of which is included in the Employment Committee files. Other materials include correspondence; legal documents; policy and position statements; press kits and press releases; legislative bills and priorities; reports; transcripts; event flyers; and voting records.
  Lesbian Rights Committee: Materials related to this committee include correspondence, proposed civil laws, committee proposals, memorandum, meeting minutes, press releases, reports, event flyers, legislative bills, and a consciousness-raising kit.
  Lesbian Sexuality Committee: Materials related to this committee include event flyers.
  Marriage and Divorce Committee: This committee was formed in 1968 and later became the Family Relations Committee in 1978. This committee offered legal advice and referrals to women experiencing divorces. The committee also worked to change existing divorce laws that placed women at a disadvantage in the courtroom. This committee organized the 1974 NOW State Conference on Marriage and Divorce; and produced the report, "The Family Court: How It Is, But Not How It Should Be." Materials related to this committee include subject files, clippings, correspondence, event flyers, annotated copies of legislative bills, press releases, legal resources, legal documents, transcriptions, and voting records.
  Membership Committee: Materials include brochures, correspondence, membership forms, membership lists, fact sheets, memorandum, committee guidelines, and requests for information about NOW-NYC.
  Minority Women's Issues Committee: The two main goals of this committee were to eliminate racism within the feminist movement; and to bring minority women and men into the feminist movement fighting both sexism and racism. Materials related to this committee include correspondence, meeting minutes, subject files, notes, memorandum, press releases, reports, recommendations, event flyers, and resources.
  Multicultural Affairs Committee: The main goals of this committee was to work in coalition with other community organizations within the various cultures of the city; to recruit for ethnic and cultural diversity within NOW; to increase the visibility of Women of Color within NOW and in general; and to work in coalition with other committees within NOW. Materials related to this committee include committee plans and event flyers.
  Newspaper Committee: This committee was responsible for writing, editing, and producing NOW-NYC's monthly chapter newspaper, The NOW York Woman. Materials related to this committee include directories, correspondence, draft articles, and memorandum.
  NOW-NYC Issues Committee: Materials related to this committee include event flyers.
  Over-45 Committee: In 1971, when this committee was first formed, the main focus was employment discrimination. This committee worked closely with another group, the Older Women's Liberation (OWL), and eventually, OWL published Volume 1, Number 2 of the Over-45 Committee's newsletter, "Prime Time." Although the 1972 conference, "OWL Speaks Out for Change for All Women," bears OWL's name, NOW-NYC was an active participant of the conference. The committee later changed its name to the Midlife and Older Women's Issues Committee and sponsored the conference, "A Time for Changes and Choices: A Conference for Midlife and Older Women." Materials related to these committees include brochures, correspondence, directories, fact sheets, announcements, agendas, meeting minutes, subject files, conference materials, and event flyers.
  Program Committee: Materials related to this committee include minutes from a meeting of thirty black women who gathered to discuss their issues as black women in the feminist movement. At this meeting, they formed the Program Committee.
  Provisional Committee on Domestic Violence: The goal of this committee was to act as an action committee responding to domestic violence impacting victims residing in New York City and NOW-NYC. Materials related to this committee include official statements, research materials, memorandums, correspondence, legislative bills, proposals, and meeting minutes.
  Psychology and Psychotherapy Committee: This committee met to discuss problems of female psychotherapy (the committee's term) and to facilitate the development of feminist psychological theories. The committee operated a psychotherapy referral service for its members and certain meetings were set aside for the discussion of personal psychotherapy experiences. In 1978, this group renamed itself the Psychology Committee and published the sixteen-page booklet, "A Consumer's Guide to Nonsexist Therapy." Materials related to this committee include correspondence, mission statements, progress reports, meeting minutes, resources, and survey results.
  Public Relations Committee: This committee produced press releases for committee actions, for outside press, and the NOW newsletter. Materials related to this committee include correspondence; fact sheets; press releases, press kits, and a press handbook; lists of press contacts; clippings; and layouts for brochures and flyers.
  Rape Prevention Committee: In 1973, this committee successfully helped to repeal New York State's corroboration requirement under which a rape victim had to prove through third-person evidence that she was raped. On behalf of the committee, Mary Vasiliades testified before the state legislature in November 1973 and the committee sent petitions to the New York governor. Notable materials related to this committee include a ten-page report by 1974 coordinator Mary Scott Welch upon leaving her position; correspondence between the 1976 committee coordinator Luba Fineson Zimmermann and Justice Edward Greenfield of the New York State Supreme Court over his decision in the Martin Evans rape trial; the committee's newsletter, "Rape Line," which was renamed "The Rape Issue" on January 15, 1975; and the yearly typed files for this committee with commentary by Mary Scott Welch that often addressed the then-current coordinator, Yolanda Bako, in the form of suggestions. Materials related to this committee include brochures, clippings, subject files, correspondence, event flyers, legislative bills, meeting minutes, newsletters, petitions, press releases, reports, resolutions. (See also the NP Collection, which includes material on the "Focus 15" slide show, including 5 slides, a "Focus 15" name tag, and numerous cassettes of the WBAI rape conference in 1975 and other shows.)
  Sex Education, Contraception, and Abortion Committee: This committee was founded in 1969 and underwent two name changes. Between 1971-1975, the committee was known as the Reproduction and Its Control Committee and in 1976, the committee changed its name to the Reproductive Rights Committee. This committee worked to repeal all abortion-related laws and make contraception widely available. Beginning in 1971, this committee began working with larger coalitions that formed to fight and repeal restrictive abortion legislation such as the Women's National Abortion Action Coalition (WONAAC). In 1973, the committee demonstrated for abortion and contraception at the annual convention of the American Medical Association. This committee continued to organize and participate in demonstrations to support abortion rights annually from 1979 to 1982. In 1981, they organized a phone bank; a petition campaign; and a public-opinion-messages campaign to send pro-choice messages to state and federal legislators. Materials related to this committee include event flyers, fact sheets, subject files, press releases, reports, correspondence, statements of legislative goals and legislative activity, clippings, legal documents, legislative bills, position statements, reports, and resolutions.
  Sexism and Religion Committee: Materials related to this committee include clippings, correspondence, and press releases.
  Sexuality Committee: Materials related to this committee include memorandum, event flyers, correspondence, conference materials, and project materials.
  Sexuality and Lesbianism Committee: In 1971, Shere Hite sent out questionnaires on sexuality under the auspices of the "Feminist Sexuality Project." This questionnaire led to the development of an ad hoc committee in April 1973 and the creation of a standing committee in September 1974. During this time, the committee organized conferences. In 1976, the committee was renamed as the Sexuality and Interpersonal Relations Committee. Materials related to this committee include workshop materials, conference announcements, programs, and correspondence.
  Structural Review Task Force: The committee was established to study the structure of NOW. Materials related to this committee include event flyers, memorandum, and fact sheets.
  Women in Prison Committee: Materials related to this committee include event flyers and memorandum.
  Youth NOW Committee: This committee recruited young feminists of high school and college age with the objective of teaching them about feminist issues. This committee later became the Young Women and Girls Committee. Materials related to this committee include press releases, correspondence, even flyers, and notes.
  Files are arranged alphabetically by committee name and then chronologically, when applicable.
  Separated Materials
  Committee newsletters have been separated and are to be catalogued with Tamiment's periodicals.
  - Ad Hoc Committee -- Artists, Writers, and Musicians, 1970, 1972 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Ad Hoc Committee -- Sports, 1972-1973 (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Ad Hoc Committee -- Sports, 1975 (Box 116, Folder 4)
  - Ad Hoc Committee -- Sports -- Billie Jean King, 1981 (Box 116, Folder 5)
  - Ad Hoc Committee -- Women and Health, 1975-1976 (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Ad Hoc Committee -- Women and Health, 1977 (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - Ad Hoc Committee -- Women and Health, 1980 (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - Ad Hoc Committee -- Women and Health Committee, 1970-1986 (Box 116, Folder 8)
  - Ad Hoc Committee -- Women and Health Committee -- AIDS Education, 1991 (Box 116, Folder 9)
  - Ad Hoc Committee -- Women and Health Committee -- Closure of NYC Mammography Center, 2002 (Box 116, Folder 10)
  - Ad Hoc Committee -- Women and Health Committee -- Playing It Safe: Sexual Negotiations in the Age of AIDS, 1987 (Box 116, Folder 11)
  - Ad Hoc Committee -- Women and Health Committee -- Resources, 1978-1979 (Box 116, Folder 12)
  - Ad Hoc Committee -- Women and Health Committee -- Risers, NOW Fitness Classes, 1981 (Box 116, Folder 13)
  - Ad Hoc Committee -- Women and Poverty, 1974 (Box 10, Folder 8)
  - Ad Hoc Committee -- Women and Volunteerism (Task Force), 1973 (Box 10, Folder 9)
  - Ad Hoc Committee -- XYZ Committee, 1972 (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Arts Committee, 1969-1971 (Box 10, Folder 10)
  - Arts Committee, 1972 (Box 10, Folder 11)
  - Arts Committee, 1972-1973 (Box 72, Folder 9)
  - Arts Committee, 1974 (Box 10, Folder 12)
  - Arts Committee -- A Documentary Herstory of Women Artists in Revolution, 1971 (Box 72, Folder 10)
  - Arts Committee -- Festival of Women's Films Poster, 1972 (Flat-file-folder 1 Right)
  - Arts Committee -- Flyers and Programs, 1972, 1974 (Box 107, Folder 1, Box Shared Tamiment 194, Folder 3)
  - Bicentennial Committee, 1975 (Box 72, Folder 11-12)
  - Bylaws Committee, 1985-1986 (Box 73, Folder 1, Box 153, Folder 2)
  - Campaign 2004 Committee (Box 73, Folder 2)
  - Child Care Committee, 1969 (Box 10, Folder 13)
  - Child Care Committee, 1970 (Box 10, Folder 14)
  - Child Care Committee, 1971 (Box 10, Folder 15)
  - Child Care Committee, 1971, 1973 (Box 73, Folder 3)
  - Child Care Committee, 1972 (Box 10, Folder 16)
  - Child Care Committee, 1973-1974 (Box 10, Folder 17)
  - Consciousness Raising Committee, 1971-1973 (Box 10, Folder 18)
  - Consciousness Raising Committee, 1976-1984 (Box 10, Folder 20)
  - Consciousness Raising Committee -- About and Guidelines, 1973, 1979 (Box 73, Folder 4)
  - Consciousness Raising Committee -- Event Flyers, 1976, 1993 (Box 73, Folder 5)
  - Consciousness Raising Committee -- Goals and Plans, 1981, 1986-1988 (Box 73, Folder 6)
  - Consciousness Raising Committee -- Meeting Minutes, 2000 (Box 73, Folder 7)
  - Consciousness Raising Committee -- Members List, 1973 (Box 10, Folder 19)
  - Consciousness Raising Committee -- Memorandum, 1989-1990 (Box 73, Folder 8)
  - Consciousness Raising Committee -- Miscellaneous, undated (Box 10, Folder 21)
  - Consciousness Raising Committee -- Reports, 1988 (Box 73, Folder 9)
  - Consciousness Raising Committee -- Saturday Night Raps, 1979 (Box 73, Folder 10)
  - Domestic Relations Committee, 1983-1990 (Box 73, Folder 11-12)
  - Education Committee, 1970 (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Education Committee, 1971 (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Education Committee, 1972 (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - Education Committee, 1973 (Box 11, Folder 8)
  - Education Committee, 1974 (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - Education Committee, 1975 (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - Education Committee, 1977 (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - Education Committee -- Bibliographies of Feminist Books, 1972-1973 (Box 73, Folder 13)
  - Education Committee -- Child Welfare, 1984, 1989 (Box 73, Folder 14)
  - Education Committee -- Correspondence, 1984-1985 (Box 74, Folder 1)
  - Education Committee -- Education Action Conference, Dec. 9, 1973 (Box 11, Folder 9)
  - Education Committee -- Education Surveys of Junior High and High Schools, 1971 (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - Education Committee -- Event Flyers, undated (Box 74, Folder 2)
  - Education Committee -- Gender Bias in Schools, 1974-1975 (Box 74, Folder 3)
  - Education Committee -- Memorandum, 1980 (Box 74, Folder 4)
  - Education Committee -- Press Releases, undated (Box 74, Folder 5)
  - Education Committee -- "Report on Sex Bias in the Public Schools", 1971-1972 (Box 74, Folder 6)
  - Education Committee -- "Report on Sex Bias in the Public Schools" -- First Edition, 1971 (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - Education Committee -- "Report on Sex Bias in the Public Schools" -- Second Edition, 1972 (Box 11, Folder 7)
  - Education Committee -- "Report on Sex Bias in the Public Schools" -- Third Edition, 1973 (Box 11, Folder 10)
  - Education Committee -- "Report on Sex Bias in the Public Schools" -- Fourth Edition, 1977 (Box 12, Folder 5)
  - Education Committee -- "Report on Sex Bias in the Public Schools" -- Selected Requests, 1973 (Box 11, Folder 11)
  - Education Committee -- "Report on Sex Bias in the Public Schools" -- Selected Requests, 1974 (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - Education Committee -- Sex Equity in Education, 1986 (Box 74, Folder 7)
  - Education Committee -- Single Sex Education, 1997, 2002 (Box 74, Folder 8)
  - Education Committee -- Symposium on Finding a Path to Gender, 1997 (Box 74, Folder 9)
  - Education Committee -- Textbook Liberation Group, 1970-1974 (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Education Committee -- "Token Learning: A Study of Women's Higher Education in America", 1968 (Box 74, Folder 10)
  - Education Committee -- Women's Colleges, 1981, 1985 (Box 74, Folder 11)
  - Education Committee -- Women's Studies, 1972-1973, 1979-1980 (Box 74, Folder 12)
  - Elections Committee, 1984-1985 (Box 74, Folder 13)
  - Eliminating Racism Committee, undated (Box 74, Folder 14)
  - Employment Committee, 1968 (Box 12, Folder 6)
  - Employment Committee, 1970 (Box 12, Folder 7)
  - Employment Committee, 1971 (Box 12, Folder 8)
  - Employment Committee, 1971-1990 (Box 74, Folder 15-16)
  - Employment Committee, 1972 (Box 12, Folder 9)
  - Employment Committee, 1973 (Box 12, Folder 10)
  - Employment Committee, 1974 (Box 12, Folder 11)
  - Employment Committee, 1975 (Box 12, Folder 12)
  - Employment Committee, 1976 (Box 12, Folder 13)
  - Employment Committee, 1977 (Box 12, Folder 14)
  - Employment Committee, 1978 (Box 12, Folder 15)
  - Employment Committee, 1979-1980 (Box 12, Folder 16)
  - Employment Committee -- Affirmative Action, 1971-1986 (Box 75, Folder 1-3)
  - Employment Committee -- Age Discrimination in Employment Act, 1980 (Box 75, Folder 4)
  - Employment Committee -- Agenda, undated (Box 75, Folder 5)
  - Employment Committee -- "Aging: A Woman's Issue" Conference, 1981 (Box 75, Folder 6)
  - Employment Committee -- Ascertainment Luncheon, 1980 (Box 75, Folder 7)
  - Employment Committee -- Attorney Referral Information, 1977-1980 (Box 75, Folder 8)
  - Employment Committee -- Blank Job Discrimination Information Forms, undated (Box 75, Folder 9)
  - Employment Committee -- Career Counseling Resources, 1979-1980 (Box 75, Folder 10)
  - Employment Committee -- Colgate-Palmolive Boycott, 1968 (Box 75, Folder 11)
  - Employment Committee -- Complaints About Sexist Job Postings, 1980 (Box 75, Folder 12)
  - Employment Committee -- Correspondence, 1972-1990 (Box 76, Folder 1-4)
  - Employment Committee -- Displaced Homemaker Program, undated (Box 76, Folder 5)
  - Employment Committee -- Equal Employment Opportunity Clause and Cable Television Franchise Agreement, 1981-1982 (Box 76, Folder 6)
  - Employment Committee -- Equal Employment Opportunity Programs and Legislation, 1978 (Box 76, Folder 7)
  - Employment Committee -- Equal Rights for Waitresses!, 1976 (Box 76, Folder 8)
  - Employment Committee -- Event Flyers, undated (Box 76, Folder 9)
  - Employment Committee --"Going Strong! Women in Defense", 1984 (Box 76, Folder 10)
  - Employment Committee -- Guidelines on Discrimination Because of Sex, circa 1972 (Box 77, Folder 1)
  - Employment Committee -- Handwritten Notes, undated (Box 77, Folder 2)
  - Employment Committee -- Job Development and Referrals, undated (Box 77, Folder 3)
  - Employment Committee -- "Job Equality Now", 1975 (Box 77, Folder 4)
  - Employment Committee -- Legal Resources, 1979 (Box 77, Folder 5)
  - Employment Committee -- Legislation, 1984-1985 (Box 77, Folder 6)
  - Employment Committee -- Mandatory Arbitration, 2001 (Box 77, Folder 7)
  - Employment Committee -- Meeting Notes, 1978-1979 (Box 77, Folder 8)
  - Employment Committee -- "Merchant of Shame" Campaigns, circa 2002 (Box 77, Folder 9, Box 153, Folder 3)
  - Employment Committee -- New York City Commission on Human Rights, 1988-1989, 1993 (Box 77, Folder 10)
  - Employment Committee -- New York State Division of Human Rights, 1970-1972 (Box 77, Folder 11)
  - Employment Committee -- New York State Division of Human Rights Press Statements, 1978 (Box 77, Folder 12)
  - Employment Committee -- New York State Worker's Rights Resources, 1975-1979, 1983-1984 (Box 77, Folder 13, Box 78, Folder 1-2)
  - Employment Committee -- NOW's Job Equality, 1975 (Box 78, Folder 3)
  - Employment Committee -- Office of Federal Contract Compliance Programs (OFCCP), 1977-1978 (Box 78, Folder 4)
  - Employment Committee -- Outside Events, 1984-1985 (Box 78, Folder 5)
  - Employment Committee -- Pay Equity, 1986 (Box 78, Folder 6)
  - Employment Committee -- Port Authority of New York and New Jersey, 1979-1980 (Box 78, Folder 7)
  - Employment Committee -- Pregnancy and Maternity Rights, 1978-1979, 1984 (Box 78, Folder 8)
  - Employment Committee -- Press Releases, 1983 (Box 78, Folder 9)
  - Employment Committee -- Public Hearing on Equal Employment Opportunities (EEO) for Women, 1972 (Box 78, Folder 10)
  - Employment Committee -- Sex Discrimination, 1970-1974, 1977, 1980-1986 (Box 78, Folder 11, Box 79, Folder 1)
  - Employment Committee -- Sex Discrimination at FMC Corporation, 1971-1972 (Box 79, Folder 2)
  - Employment Committee -- Summary Report of New York Task Force on Women in the Courts, 1986 (Box 79, Folder 3)
  - Employment Committee -- Teachers, 1976 (Box 79, Folder 4)
  - Employment Committee -- Volunteers, 1974 (Box 79, Folder 5)
  - Employment Committee -- Women in the Workforce and Equal Pay Resources, 1978 (Box 79, Folder 6)
  - Employment Committee -- Women's Role in Contemporary American Society (Open Hearings), 1970 (Box 79, Folder 7)